A Guide to the Francis Nicholson Papers, Addition One, 1695-1765.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Papers, Addition One, 1695-1765.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 86.10
17 items.
Nicholson, Francis, 1655-1728.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1986.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Nicholson was a member of the Council for the Dominion of New England and in 1688 was commissioned lieutenant governor of the Dominion. Served as lieutenant governor of New York (1688), lieutenant governor of Virginia (1690-1692), governor of Maryland (1694-1698), governor of Virginia (1698-1705) governor of Nova Scotia (1713-1717), and governor of South Carolina (1721-1725. He was a fellow of the Royal Society.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains letters, 1696-1724, written to Francis Nicholson as governor of Maryland and South Carolina by the Bishop of London (Henry Compton) concerning Anglican ministers, and citing the example of Virginia [College of William and Mary?] in advising him about his school in Maryland (King William's School, later St. John's University, Annapolis); by the Archbishop of Canterbury (William Wake) advising him not to return to England to answer imputations; by Walter Cary concerning court politics, [Sir Robert?] Walpole, and the death of Sir Charles Cook; by Peter H[?] discussing French events; by [?] Jackson concerning the loss of a ship; by Elloys Knight, recounting a journey; by E[lizabeth] Sa[vage] on plots against King William III, and mentioning [William] Pen[n] as an enemy of Nicholson; and by an unidentified person detailing a conspiracy against the king by trying to affect the election of sheriffs of London and Middlesex. There are also papers, 1731-1765, that concern the will of Francis Nicholson in which he left his estate to the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts including letters of David Humphrey, M. Howard, Jacob Henderson, and a legal opinion of P[hillip] Yorke.
Arrangement
Items arranged chronologically.
Related Materials at the John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library:
See also MS 43.4, the Francis Nicholson Papers, 1680-1721.
Index Terms
Persons:
Cary, Walter.; Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.; Cook, Charles, Sir.; Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of, 1690-1764.; Henderson, Jacob, ca. 1681- 1751.; Humphreys, David, 1689-1740.; Knight, Elloys.; Penn, William, 1644-1718.; Savage, Elizabeth.; Wake, William, 1657-1737.; Walpole, Robert, Earl of Orford, 1676-1745.
Corporate Names:
St. John's University (Annapolis, Md.); College of William and Mary.; Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts (Great Britain).
Subjects:
Evangelicalism --Church of England --History --18th Century.; Governors -- Maryland.; Governors -- South Carolina.
Geographical Names:
Great Britain --History --William and Mary, 1689-1702.
Contents List
- Letter. Peter Haset (?) to Governor Francis Nicholson, Annapolis, Maryland re English governmental policies, events and gossip. 10 February 1695/6.
- Letter. London, Peter (?) Jackson to Col. Francis Nicholson. 17 January 1697. 26 January [1696/7].
- Letter. H. London (Henry Compton, Bishop of London) to Francis Nicholson re schools in Maryland. 5 January 1698.
- Letter. Ellway Knight to Francis Nicholson, Governor of South Carolina. 27 January 1720.
- Letter. Walter Cary, London, to Francis Nicholson re attempted meetings with Lord Townscend and deaths in London. 28 February 1720.
- Anonymous agent's report to Francis Nicholson re conspiracies relating to the election of the sheriff of London. Ca. 1722-1723.
- Letter. [Arch. Bishop of Canterbury], Lambeth House, to Francis Nicholson. 10 February 1723/4.
- Letter. D.H. [Rev. David Humphries], London, Secretary for the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts, to Mr. Bordley, Maryland, re land Francis Nicholson will the S.P.G. in Maryland. 24 February 1731.
- Letter. Unsigned [Rev. David Humphries], London, to Rev. Jacob Henderson, Maryland, re Francis Nicholson lands in Maryland. 24 February 1731.
- Letter. Rev. David Humphries, London, to Jacob Henderson, Maryland, re Francis Nicholson lands in Maryland. 26 March 1731.
- Letter. William Howard, Attorney General of Maryland, to Rev. Jacob Henderson, Maryland re Francis Nicholson land in Maryland. 5 August 1732.
- Letter. Rev. Jacob Henderson, Maryland, to David Humphries, London, re possible lawsuit over Francis Nicholson lands in Maryland. 16 August 1732.
- Letter. Jacob Henderson, Maryland, to David Humphries, London, re Francis Nicholson land in Maryland. 24 October 1732.
- Legal Opinion of P. Yorke re Francis Nicholson will and the bequeathment of lands in America to the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel. 26 December 1732.
- Extracts of accounts including the legacy of Gov. Francis Nicholson's will. 1765.
- Memorandum re items willed the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel. N.D. (ca. 1735).